PAUL JAY: Welcome back to Reality Asserts
Itself. I'm Paul Jay, and this is The Real
News Network.
We're continuing our series of interviews
with John Kiriakou. We're at his house, as
I've said before. He's--continues to be under
house arrest as we do these interviews.
John was the first CIA officer to officially
confirm that there was in fact a waterboarding
torture program. He's also the only person
that went to jail for anything to do with
the waterboarding torture program, and that
was because he was the first person to officially
confirm there was a waterboarding torture
program. Unfortunately, the people who were
actually doing the waterboarding and ordering
the waterboarding didn't go to jail and never
kept him any company in jail.
Thanks for joining us.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: So let's pick up our story from that.
Why did the CIA target you?
KIRIAKOU: The CIA never forgive me for confirming
that it was waterboarding and otherwise torturing
prisoners, that that torture was official
U.S. government policy, and that the policy
was approved by the president. Never forgive
me.
JAY: So where did you say this, and how did
you get [incompr.]
KIRIAKOU: I said this in December 2007 on
ABC News. And it started oddly for me. I got
a call from Brian Ross.
JAY: Let me just back up one sec, 'cause we've
been kind of doing your story chronologically;
now we're kind of jumping.
KIRIAKOU: Okay.
JAY: So if I understand correctly, you left
the CIA in what year?
KIRIAKOU: In 2004.
JAY: Two thousand and four.
KIRIAKOU: Mhm.
JAY: And you did some consulting. You did
consulting for ABC.
KIRIAKOU: Not yet. I left the CIA in 2004
and I joined Deloitte & Touche, which is one
of the big four public accounting firms.
JAY: Okay. So, first of all, why did you leave
the CIA?
KIRIAKOU: I left the CIA, as funny as it might
sound, to spend more time with my children.
I had gone through a very acrimonious divorce.
My ex-wife had moved to Northeastern Ohio
with my two sons so that she could be closer
to her parents. And I knew that my career
was going to take me back overseas again in
short order, and to someplace not family-friendly--Iraq,
Afghanistan, Pakistan, Yemen, something like
that. And so I decided I had had enough.
And I had a friend who had a friend at Deloitte
& Touche, one of the big four accounting firms.
They were looking for someone to head counter--not
counterintelligence, but competitive intelligence
in their Washington, D.C., office. And I applied
for the job, and a couple of weeks later was
made an offer. I resigned from the CIA, and
the very next day went into Deloitte & Touche.
JAY: Why does Deloitte Touche want a CIA guy?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I was actually the fourth
CIA guy that Deloitte & Touche had hired.
They had created this group called the Competitive
Intelligence Group, with the idea being that
they would hire former CIA officers or other
people with experience in intelligence collection,
and they would pair those people with the
analysts, the corporate research analysts,
to collect and analyze intelligence on their
competitors.
So my job was to collect first-person human-source
intelligence on Ernst & Young, KPMG, PricewaterhouseCoopers,
and a myriad of consulting firms, like IBM
and Accenture and others. And we would collect
this information. Sometimes they were tips.
JAY: For example?
KIRIAKOU: Well, for example, we tried to steal
their pricing models or how they determined
discounts. Or, interestingly, at least to
me, we tried to figure out which of their
partners were disgruntled so we could steal
them, provided that they were top producers.
JAY: And I'm assuming they're all doing it
back to Deloitte Touche, everyone's doing
this to each other.
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely. They all have the same
groups. Now, I will say that Deloitte's no
longer exists. It went away during the recession.
But the other consulting firms, yes, they
do have similar groups.
JAY: And are they looking for dirt on individuals?
KIRIAKOU: No. No.
JAY: Or this is more about recruitment?
KIRIAKOU: It's much more about recruitment.
And it's also about undercutting pricing.
If you're going to go into a bid with a price
of $24 million, let's say, we want to know
that so we can go in with a bid of $20 million
and win the job, because a $20 million contract
of course is better than a zero dollar contract.
JAY: And so they're all doing it to each other.
So this is a lot about the bidding process,
then, trying to get someone to spill the beans
on a bid.
KIRIAKOU: Yes. The bidding process--.
JAY: It's like recruiting a double agent.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. It's the bidding process.
It's discounts. It's disgruntled partners,
like I said. It's plans to expand service
lines or offerings. Anything that might give
you a corporate leg up.
JAY: And were you successful?
KIRIAKOU: Wildly, in some cases.
JAY: Really? Alright. That's--we'll do that
another day.
KIRIAKOU: Okay.
JAY: Okay. So then what? Deloitte Touche.
At what point do you start consulting for
ABC?
KIRIAKOU: Not until after I went on TV and
talked about torture. I was at my desk at
Deloitte one day and I got a call from Brian
Ross at ABC News. And Brian Ross told me that
he had a source who said that I had tortured
Abu Zubaydah. I said that was absolutely untrue,
that I was the only person who was ever kind
to Abu Zubaydah, and I said I never have laid
a hand on anybody, least of all Abu Zubaydah.
And he said--and I learned later that this
was an old reporter's trick--he said, well,
you can come on the show and defend yourself.
In the meantime, that same day, the day before,
the same week, whatever it was, President
Bush was telling the press that we do not
torture, we do not torture, we do not torture.
GEORGE W. BUSH: This government does not torture
people. You know, we stick to U.S. law and
our international obligations.
Thirdly, there are highly trained professionals
questioning these extremists and terrorists.
We've got professionals who are trained in
this kind of work to get information that'll
protect the American people.
And by the way, we have gotten information
from these high-value detainees that have
helped protect you.
KIRIAKOU: I knew that was a lie.
And then, later, he said that we don't torture,
but if there is torture, it's the result of
a rogue CIA officer or a rogue operation.
I knew that was a lie.
So I went on ABC news. And he never even asked
me on camera if I had tortured Abu Zubaydah.
He just went straight into the torture.
KIRIAKOU: And at the time, I felt that waterboarding
was something we needed to do. And as time
has passed and as September 11 has moved farther
and farther back into history, I think I've
changed my mind and I think that waterboarding's
probably something that we shouldn't be in
the business of doing.
BRIAN ROSS, JOURNALIST, ABC NEWS: Why do you
say that now?
KIRIAKOU: Because we're Americans and we're
better than that.
ROSS: But at the time, you didn't feel that
way.
KIRIAKOU: At the time, I was so angry and
I wanted so much to help disrupt future attacks
on the United States that I felt it was the
only thing we could do.
ROSS: And with Zubaydah you think that was
successful.
KIRIAKOU: It was.
ROSS: And we have reported that Khalid Sheikh
Mohammed was also waterboarded.
KIRIAKOU: I was out of it by then, but it's
my understanding that he was also waterboarded.
ROSS: But those were really the only two.
KIRIAKOU: To the best of my knowledge, yes.
ROSS: And bottom line, as you sit here now,
do you think that was worth it?
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
ROSS: Did it compromise American principles,
or did it save American lives, or both?
KIRIAKOU: It--I think both. It may have compromised
our principles, at least in the short term.
And I think it's good that we're having a
national debate about this. We should be debating
this and Congress should be talking about
it, because I think as a country we have to
decide if this is something that we want to
do as a matter of policy. I'm not saying now
that we should, but at the very least we should
be talking about it. It shouldn't be secret.
It should be out there as part of the national
debate.
KIRIAKOU: In that interview, I essentially
called the president of the United States
a liar. In fact, the next day, at a press
conference--.
DANA PERINO: I am saying that the United States
does not torture. The president has been--.
JOURNALIST: I'm asking you if what was done
in this case was not torture, in your opinion.
PERINO: I'm saying the United States does
not torture.
JOURNALIST: But we have a former CIA officer,
John Kiriakou, now saying that waterboarding
was used. And you're saying the interrogations
were legal. He's saying on the record now
waterboarding was used in at least one case.
You're saying waterboarding is legal?
PERINO: Ed, I'm saying I'm not commenting
on any specific technique. I'm not commenting
on that gentleman's characteristics of any
possible technique. I have given you a very
general statement about interrogations being
legal, limited [crosstalk]
JOURNALIST: [crosstalk] was legal.
PERINO: I'm sorry?
JOURNALIST: You said--was it in the legal
framework?
PERINO: Yes.
JOURNALIST: Everything that was done?
JOURNALIST: So waterboarding is legal.
PERINO: I'm not commenting on any specific
techniques. And you can ask me all sorts of
different ways and we can go back and forth,
but I'm not going to do it, Ed.
KIRIAKOU: Well, immediately the CIA filed
what's called a crimes report with the Justice
Department, alleging that I had violated my
secrecy agreement by leaking classified information.
The FBI investigated, they watched the tape,
and they concluded that it was already common
knowledge that we were torturing prisoners.
Human Rights Watch had come out with a report.
Amnesty International had come out with a
report. So I had added nothing, technically,
to the debate.
But what I had done was I had become the first
CIA officer, current or former, to actually
confirm that we were torturing prisoners and
that torture was our policy.
JAY: Now, when you first talked about it,
you defend torture, do you not? There's a
point where you say he's been tortured, waterboarded
once.
KIRIAKOU: A lot of people think that I was
defending it. In fact, I was trying to be
nuanced, and I failed at being nuanced. I
was trying to present it as two questions,
two separate issues. One, did it work? And
two, was it right? And I said it wasn't right,
it was wrong morally and ethically, that it
was torture and that I was opposed to it.
In fact, I had been asked by a senior officer
in the Counterterrorism Center if I wanted
to be certified in the use of these so-called
enhanced interrogation techniques, and I declined.
I said I had a moral problem with it.
On that first question, did it work, the CIA
officers in the field who were torturing prisoners
were reporting back that it was working and
that Abu Zubaydah, for example, had cracked
after one session, one waterboarding session,
and that he had given up actionable information
that saved American lives.
JAY: And that's what--when you're on television,
that's what you knew at that time.
KIRIAKOU: That's what I knew at that time.
JAY: So you conclude that it was done once
and it worked.
KIRIAKOU: Correct; although it was wrong,
it had worked. We didn't know, nobody knew,
until the CIA inspector general report was
released in April 2009 that said that, no,
he was waterboarded 83 times and Khalid Sheikh
Mohammed was waterboarded 147 times. So they
were even lying to each other internally to
try to justify this thing.
So I told Brian Ross what I thought I knew
as facts, but I was wrong.
JAY: So what's the next big beat for you?
Is it the inspector general's report?
KIRIAKOU: Well, yeah. In that year, 2008 to
early 2009, I ended up consulting for ABC
News. And, frankly, what I had done is I called
Brian Ross and I said, you ruined my life;
the least you could do is throw me a little
bit of work. And so ABC brought me on as a
consultant.
In early 2009, John Kerry offered me a job
as the senior investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. So I was under the impression
that he actually wanted me to investigate
things. And I ran into even more trouble with
the CIA in that job.
JAY: Now, between going on TV and acknowledging
that there is torture, they open a file on
you, and the inspector general's report, and
Kerry's job, how actively are they pursuing
you and how aware are you of it?
KIRIAKOU: I was unaware of any investigation
aimed at me, targeting me. It turned out that
they never stopped investigating me from December
2007 until my arrest in 2012.
JAY: Prior to you going on television, was
there any sense that the CIA wasn't happy
with you?
KIRIAKOU: Oh, no, none. On the contrary, when
I was at Deloitte & Touche, they were preparing
to bid for a job in the CIA's Counterterrorism
Center. I still had an active security clearance
at the time, and so they asked if they could
add me to the list of cleared individuals
that might participate in this contract. I
said yes, and I called the security officer
at the Counterterrorism Center, and she said,
yeah, that's great with us. And I ended up
not doing it, because my boss was willing
to give me up for six weeks, but they wanted
me for six months until the contract really
got going. But I had no problems whatsoever
with the CIA until I went on ABC.
JAY: 'Cause you'd think if they had no issues
with you and you say this one thing on TV,
they would say, oh, look, this guy's been
a stellar agent all this time and never--and
so on, and everyone already knows it's happening;
we could just, like, ignore it.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: But by targeting you, they're making
it 100 times more an issue, even in the public
eye. And eventually it's going to go public.
I mean, look where it's led to, all these
interviews [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Well, that's why I maintain the
CIA is the organization that made me a human
rights activist. It's the CIA that's made
me want to take to the streets to defend our
civil liberties. Otherwise, I wouldn't have
given it two minutes of thought. But you're
exactly right.
And even if they were angry, there are other
cases of CIA officers, current CIA officers,
exposing classified information. And what
happens to them is they get a letter in their
file and they don't get promoted for a year.
They don't get seven felony charges--or five
felony charges.
JAY: So I go back to my first question: why
target you in this way?
KIRIAKOU: I think that the targeting came
from inside the Counterterrorism Center. It
wasn't necessarily the CIA as an organization,
as a whole; it was CTC. CTC was run by cowboys
and hardasses. And I think that they were
so furious, that what I had done was unforgivable,
that they are the ones who asked the Justice
Department to go after me.
JAY: CTC is this thing we see on this TV show
24, right?
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: That's--I mean, does it bear any resemblance
to reality, the 24 room?
KIRIAKOU: No. The room? No. No, that's all
Hollywood.
JAY: Okay. So let's jump ahead. The inspector
general's report comes out. You find out that
it wasn't once; it was 83 times.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: And in fact the intelligence wasn't actionable.
So what does that do to you? And what are
you doing at the time?
KIRIAKOU: Well, frankly, it makes me look
like a fool. At the time, I was working for
John Kerry. I had only been there about a
month, maybe six weeks. But it made me look
like a fool.
But I issued a statement saying I gave the
facts as I knew them. I think that the inspector
general's report shows that the CIA will lie
to its own staff officers. I had no regrets.
JAY: Two years had gone by. So why does this
eventually lead to a charge? I don't get--I
mean, how--.
KIRIAKOU: While I was at the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee, I decided to do some
real investigations. So at first I wanted
to investigate what was called the Dasht-i-Leili
massacre. This was an incident in northern
Afghanistan on November 30 and December 1,
2001, where the Northern Alliance had captured
as many as 2,000 Taliban soldiers and wanted
to incarcerate them. Well, there were no jails
in Afghanistan big enough to hold 2,000 prisoners
all at once. So what the Northern Alliance
decided to do was to load these men onto container
trucks and take them out into the desert,
deep into the desert, and just hold them there
until they could figure out how to get them
to different jails around the country.
JAY: This is General Dostum.
KIRIAKOU: This is General Dostum and his men.
JAY: Who's now a vice president?
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, vice president or deputy prime
minister, or one or the other. So nobody had
put any air holes in these containers, and
there was no food and there was no water.
So after an eight-hour drive into the desert--.
JAY: How many people were packed in a container?
KIRIAKOU: Two thousand people in a series
of containers. So, after eight hours' drive
into the desert, one of the witnesses who
survived told us that when they opened the
back of the tracks, that bodies fell out like
sardines out of a can. So almost everybody
died. By our count, there were 18 survivors
out of 2,000.
The reason I was interested in this is because
I had taken a call from a human rights activist
who told us that he had a witness, who was
a boy at the time and didn't go onto the truck,
and he said that the boy saw two white men
wearing jeans and black T-shirts and speaking
English at the box-up. Well, who's going to
be in Mazari Sharif, Afghanistan, speaking
English, wearing bluejeans, on November 30,
2001?
So I interviewed everybody at the State Department
at the time who mattered from 2001. I interviewed
several human rights activists. And I sent
a letter to the agency asking for some clarification.
Within a couple of days, the deputy office
director--or staff director is what he's called--at
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee told
me that the investigation was dead and to
drop it.
JAY: Just quickly, just coincidentally, I
happened to have made a documentary called
Return to Kandahar in Afghanistan in the spring
of 2002, and we interviewed General Dostum.
So here's a few seconds of that, just to give
you a sense of who we're talking about here.
NELOFER PAZIRA: In the '90s, when these guys fought each other,
over 1 million people died and half of the city of Kabul was destroyed. That's not a football game.
JAY: So that's General Dostum. Now, General Dostum clearly is--was, is a war criminal.
You had uncovered evidence that proved it.
And it gets shut down. Why?
KIRIAKOU: I think that I was poking the hornets
nest at the time. And I'm not sure if I was
doing it subconsciously or if it just worked
out that way. But I wanted to know if CIA
officers were present at the box-up. Now,
I know CIA officers were present 20 miles
away, because the box-up was the same day
as the uprising at Qala-i-Jangi, where--
JAY: This is the prison.
KIRIAKOU: --Mike Spann was killed, in the
Taliban - al-Qaeda uprising that took place
in that prison. So I know they were in the
area. I wanted to know if they were at the
box-up.
JAY: Which was another slaughter.
KIRIAKOU: It was another slaughter, yes.
So I dropped that investigation.
And then I got a call from a reporter who
told me that he had some information that
seemed to indicate that the CIA was taking
its torturers and putting them under State
Department cover.
JAY: Let's back up one sec just to close the
loop on the previous story. If you had in
fact found that there were CIA at the box-up,
they would have been implicated in a war crime.
KIRIAKOU: Correct. Correct. And that war crime
would have been detailed in an official report
from the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
JAY: Okay.
KIRIAKOU: So I moved on to another investigation.
A reporter called me and said that he had
information that the CIA was taking some of
its torturers and placing them under State
Department cover, which was a violation of
the cover agreement between the CIA and the
State Department. So I sent the State Department
a letter asking for clarification.
Weeks passed. Something like five, six weeks
passed. And finally a colleague of mine comes
into my office and says, oh, you got a response
to your letter from the agency. I said, I
didn't get any response. He said, well, they
classified it top secret, and you're not cleared
for it. I said, well, what'd they say? And
he smiles and he says, they said go fuck yourself.
So that was the end of that investigation.
JAY: So how long after all this do you get
charged?
KIRIAKOU: Well, it was another three years.
There were other investigations, too, at which
I was poking them. They even called my wife
in to the CIA security office and threatened
her.
JAY: Now, your wife--.
KIRIAKOU: My wife was a CIA officer at the
time.
JAY: Is or was?
KIRIAKOU: Was.
JAY: Was CIA. You met at the CIA.
KIRIAKOU: We met at the CIA.
JAY: So they call her in and what?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I had written an op-ed in
the Los Angeles Times in which I said that
we need to be very cautious about Iran's inroads
into Latin America; we need to improve our
relations with Latin American countries because
the Iranians are improving theirs. And I wrote
one sentence in that op-ed dealing with Iranian
travel to Latin America.
Now, I got that op-ed cleared by the CIA.
So, finally, they call my wife in to security.
And they have a camera on. And the security
guy says, this is not an investigation, it's
an inquiry, but we're going to tape it. What
do you think should be done with people who
leak classified information? (Totally loaded
question.) She said, well, what are you talking
about? Well, your husband wrote an op-ed in
the Los Angeles Times. And she said, he got
that op-ed cleared.
JAY: Let me ask, why would you have to get
it cleared? You're no longer working for the
KIRIAKOU: I have to get anything I write dealing
with intelligence, CIA, foreign affairs, government,
anything, for the rest of my life, cleared
by the CIA's Publications Review Board.
JAY: What about this interview or the other
interviews [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Well, these are written products--articles,
books, magazine articles, you know, op-eds.
JAY: Interviews are okay.
KIRIAKOU: Interviews are okay.
JAY: Alright. Go on.
KIRIAKOU: So she said, well, he got that cleared
by the Publications Review Board. And the
guy tells her, and we really appreciate that,
but there is a line in there that is top-secret.
And she said, well, that's impossible; my
husband doesn't have access to top-secret
information. And he says, but you do. So she
said, I think I've said enough. And she got
up and walked away.
JAY: What was the line?
KIRIAKOU: Well, it was that Iranians no longer
need visas to travel to Bolivia.
JAY: What?! This was top-secret?
KIRIAKOU: She was very upset. And she called
me. And I told her, take it easy. I said,
do you know where I got that information?
And she said, no. I said, I got it from the
Bolivian Foreign Ministry's website. It's
on the website.
JAY: And why on earth would it be secret anyway?
KIRIAKOU: I told her, one thing that you may
want to tell them is, number one, apparently
nobody in the CIA speaks Spanish, first of
all. Secondly, they apparently have a source
who's selling them press and calling it intelligence.
So they were upset about that.
JAY: Well, they're out to get you at this
point.
KIRIAKOU: At that point they were out to get
me. But I didn't think that this would result
in any kind of criminal charges.
JAY: It's almost sounding like when you go
public on the torture issue, they open a file.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah.
JAY: It's this stuff where they really decide,
we have to shut this guy up.
KIRIAKOU: Well, it got much, much worse. Toward
the end of my stay at the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee, there was an incident that I'll
tell you about.
Part of my job was to have--.
JAY: Okay. Hang on. This is going to be a
cliffhanger. You've got to join us for the
next part to find out what happened next on
Reality Asserts Itself on The Real News Network.
Thanks for joining us.